Phi Delta Sorority; Records ua800.009
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Phi Delta Sorority Records
1923-2004, Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Phi Delta
ua800.009
3.64 cubic ft.
The Phi Delta Sorority Records contain documents related to the history, activities and alumnae of the Phi Delta Sorority at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Annette Gardiner DeLyser, Class of 1949, President of the Phi Delta Alumnae Association.
Biographical Sketch
The sorority known as Phi Delta was officially organized as an on-campus club for women called Alpha Delta Omicron in April of 1923. The club was first recognized by the New York State College for Teachers (now the University at Albany) President, A.R. Brubacher, on November 11, 1924. Phi Delta adopted its present name in 1926 with the hopes of becoming a national women's organization. Those dreams did come true for the members of State College's Alpha chapter in February of 1927 when Phi Delta officially became a national sorority with a total of five chapters nationwide.
Phi Delta was founded as a social sorority for Protestant women. Phi Delta also had the distinction of being the first Protestant national sorority at State College. Exactly how long the sorority had a restrictive membership is unclear. Records show that by the early 1960s membership was open to both African-American and Jewish students.
The local sorority is believed to have dissolved sometime in 1972 or 1973, around the same time many other local sororities met the same fate. The Phi Delta Alumnae Association's $7,000 gift to the SUNY Albany Foundation in 1974 came with the stipulation that, if there was ever another active chapter of Phi Delta on campus, $5,000 would be made available to them. There was some interest among alumnae in reinstating an active chapter at Albany in the late 1980s and early 1990s--around the time the Chi Sigma Theta sorority launched a new active chapter on campus--but those plans never came to fruition. The Alumnae Association continued to be active, sending out newsletters and hosting get-togethers during University at Albany Homecoming and Reunion until at least the early 2000s.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains administrative and subject files such as constitutions, meeting minutes, and membership lists; scrapbooks documenting the sorority's members and activities; and memorabilia such as official sorority stamps and jewelry. Administrative files of the Alumnae Association are also included in the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 is arranged alphabetically. Series 2 is arranged chronologically.
Greek letter societies--New York (State)--Albany; Sorority songs; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Women--New York (State)--Albany--Societies and clubs; Correspondence; Photographs; Scrapbooks; UAlbany Student Groups; Minutes (administrative records); State University of New York at Albany; Phi Delta Sorority
- Administrative and Subject Files, 1923-2004; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative and subject files for the Phi Delta Sorority. It includes such materials as constitutions, initiation ceremonies and traditions, membership lists, newsletters, financial records and more, documenting the sorority's activities throughout its history. There are also similar materials relating to Phi Delta alumnae.
  - The Ado, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Association Life Member certificate, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Alumnae directories, 1949; 1960; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Alumnae directories and newsletter, 1957-1958; ca. 1966 (Oversized 1)
  - Alumnae financial records, 1982-1990; 1999; 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Alumnae lists, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Alumnae newsletters, 1963; ca. 1969 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Alumnae newsletters and invitations, 1981-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Alumnae newsletters, 2000-2003 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Alumnae reunion guestbook, 1980-2004 (Oversized 1)
  - Alumni awards, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Alumni donation correspondence, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Annual convention and meeting President Hoover, 1931 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Application for charter, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Busca el Burro program, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Cancelled bank books, 1940-1980 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Ceremonies, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Chapter and national constitutions, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Christmas Ball programs, 1949 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Committee reports for Greek workshop, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Composite photographs, 1963-1968; 1970-1971; 1977-1978 (Flat-file 1)
  - Constitution, 1923; 1967 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Constitution, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Constitution, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Correspondence and notes, 1927; 1932; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Correspondence re: alumnae newsletter, 1992; 2001-2004 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Correspondence re: constitution and traditions, ca. 1941 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Correspondence re: memorabilia, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - History, ca. 1930 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Honorary members, 1937-1952 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - House mother Lydia Totten obituary, 1962 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Housing financial and legal documents, 1956-1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Housing, Uptown Campus, 1964 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - Incorporation, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Incorporation papers, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Initiation ritual, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Invitations and program, 1948-1949 (Box 1 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Membership list, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Member lists and financial documents, 1962-1963 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Membership questionnaire, 1931-1939 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Metal type, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1945-1948 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1949-1951 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - National constituion and initiation ceremony, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings, ca. 1940s (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Newsclippings, Western Avenue house, 1946 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Newspapers, 1946; 1948 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Obituaries, 2004; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Phi Delt newsletters, 1931-1932; 1940-1942; 1947 (Oversized 1)
  - Phi Delta newsletters, 1958-1960 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1941 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Photographs, 1948 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1949 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Photographs, ca. 1960s (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Photographs, Rush party, 1952 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Photograph, sisters outside Hudson Avenue building, 1929 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Pin photographs and history, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Pledge lists, 1930-1954 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Poem, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - President Collins memo on fraternities and sororities, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Reactiviation correspondence and notes, 1985; 1992; Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Recommendations, 1929-1967 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Songs, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Songs, Undated (Oversized 1)
  - Sorority photograph, 1951 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Spring Formal dance program, 1951 (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Thank you note, Undated (Box 2 (1-Administrative and Subject Files), Folder 31)
- Scrapbooks and Memorabilia, 1929-1965; Undated; 2
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series consists of scrapbooks kept by the sorority to document activities as well as objects used by the sorority and bearing the Phi Delta seal.
  - Scrapbook, 1929 (Box 2 (2-Scrapbooks and Memorabilia), Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook, 1947-1948 (Oversized 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Oversized 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1960-1961 (Oversized 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1962 (Oversized 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1962-1963 (Oversized 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1963-1964 (Oversized 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1965 (Oversized 8)
  - Life Member seal embossing stamp, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Phi Delta bracelet, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Phi Delta jewelry box, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Phi Delta powder compact, Undated (Artifact-box 1)
  - Phi Delta seal embossing stamp, Undated (Artifact-box 1)